- [Narrator] On a normal evening in 2009,
a man gets home from work
and boots up his computer.
His name is Markus Persson,
but he often goes by
his screen name, Notch.
Based in Stockholm, Sweden,
Persson spends his evenings
developing passion projects,
fun coding exercises that sometimes
end up as completed video games,
but more typically become
abandoned after a short time.
But what he doesn't know
is that the file he starts today
will change the gaming industry forever
and will make him one of the
wealthiest suites in the world.
This is the making of "Minecraft."
(gentle electronic music)
In the very beginning,
the game that Persson was creating
wasn't called "Minecraft."
It was called "RubyDung,"
based on the two main
elements of the game,
the Ruby Lands and the Dungeons.
- [Markus] "It's going to
be a fantasy group manager.
You don't actually do any quests yourself,
but rather assemble,
equip and level up heroes,
and send among quests you've
gotten them the local town."
- [Narrator] Persson
created a texture atlas,
which is essentially one large image file
that contains lots of smaller textures.
Initially, this atlas only
contained two textures,
grass and cobblestone.
Using these elements,
he created a digital
landscape filled with trees.
Next up, Persson wanted to
implement a first person view
of the heroes going on their quests,
but quickly he realized
that it was becoming too
pixelated and blurry.
Frustrated that he couldn't
get all of the features
just quite right, Persson
scrapped the idea,
not realizing that he had just
created the first prototype
for what would later become "Minecraft."
One major limitation
was that he could only work on his games
during the limited free
time after his day job.
He worked as a programmer at Midas Player,
the Swedish game developers
that would later go on
to create "Candy Crush."
However, his bosses at Midas Player
were unsupportive of Persson's hobby,
and once they discovered
that he was making his own
games in his free time,
they felt that there
was a competing interest
and they barred him from
continuing making his own games.
But Persson couldn't be stopped.
Rather than comply, he
decided to quit his job
in order to continue working
on his own passion projects,
and he found a new job with
the software company jAlbum,
where he befriended the CEO Carl Manneh.
JAlbum was not a game studio,
but a company that made
digital photo album software.
And Carl Manneh not only didn't mind
what Persson did in his free time,
but instead he actively encouraged him
to continue designing games.
At this point, RubyDung
still sat on the shelf,
a scrap project with
little more development.
That is until April, 2009
when Persson came across a new game
that would change everything for him.
The game was called "Infiniminer."
"Infiniminer" is a multiplayer game
where players team up
against other players
to dig blocks in search of minerals.
As blocks are dug up,
they can then be used
to create structures
to impede other teams.
Though the objective of the game
was to mine up more minerals
than your opponents,
players quickly abandoned that goal
and instead realized it was much more fun
to just build things.
But despite the game's enormous potential,
its development was
plagued with difficulties.
Zachary Barth, the original
creator of "Infiniminer,"
had intended to create a
large network of players,
but with the game's code
constantly being modified and rewritten,
the game soon fragmented its user base
as the different versions of the game
weren't compatible with each other.
Frustrated, Barth decided to
abandon the project as a whole
and the game's code became open source.
The first time Persson
tried "Infiniminer,"
he immediately had an epiphany
that this was the game he wanted to do,
and he had lots of ideas of
how he could make it better.
He sat back down with the
previously abandoned "RubyDung"
and got to work tweaking it
into the new vision he had in his head.
Reusing his existing textures,
Persson took a full weekend
to rework some of the
coding and art style.
He called his creation "Cave Game"
and with just a little more work,
it moved from just a test
to a working prototype.
Now all he needed were players
and he had a plan for where he
could get some early testers.
Just a few weeks prior,
Persson joined an online indie
game forum called TIGSource.
Here, developers can receive
feedback from other developers
on games they are creating.
Persson began discussing
with others in the community
who quickly suggested a
new name for the project,
"Minecraft: Order of the Stone,"
named for the two actions
you could do in the game,
mining and crafting.
Though Persson would later drop
the subtitle from the name.
He then decided that this forum
would be the best place to
start getting early players
and have some immediate feedback
for how he could continue
developing the game.
And so on May 17th, 2009,
he shared the first link
that would allow others in the forum
to begin play testing the game.
- [Narrator 2] In "Minecraft,"
it's an alpha version,
so there might be some crashes.
- [Narrator] Just 12 minutes
after he posted the link,
the first person provides feedback.
- [Player] "Oh hell, that's pretty cool.
I just dig around on the ground a bit
and suddenly I'm in this underground cave.
Great sense of exploration already."
- [Narrator] Just three
minutes later, the next reply.
- [Player 2] "The
animations are fantastic.
It's generally really
derivative at the moment
of 'Infiniminer.'"
- [Narrator] Quickly, more and
more people are downloading,
providing feedback and above all, praise.
And though the forum
was made for feedback,
players couldn't resist posting
the things they have made.
And since people were
showing off screenshots
of their creations,
more and more people were
encouraged to jump in
and give it a try themselves.
The community also had plenty of feedback
for features that could make
"Minecraft" even better,
and Persson was on it, updating
his blog nearly every day
with the progress he was making
on adding many of the ideas presented.
- [Markus] "I plan on
having several game modes,
creative, survival, team
survival, a fortress."
- [Narrator] Though
players were consistently
finding the gameplay
addicting in this early stage,
there was no way to save
what they had built.
There was also no way to play with friends
or to play on maps that
others had created.
Persson would often sit
down with the intention
to add these commonly requested
elements to "Minecraft,"
but he would repeatedly get distracted
due to the challenges of
implementing multiplayer
and instead would focus
on more fun features.
- [Markus] "Okay, multiplayer
was boring, but here's water.
Should 'Minecraft' have blood?
No, blood is overused."
- [Narrator] Next up
was adding multiplayer,
which would take quite some time.
But Persson was determined
to get it up and running,
though not without some more
side projects along the way
and more challenges to overcome.
- [Markus] "So I didn't do
multiplayer code, but I had fun.
Multiplayer will be in the
form of a downloadable server,
which will broadcast its IP
to the main server when it starts up.
Ugh, I feel stupid.
Server admins could host any data
they want on their servers.
This means anything, including bad things.
Multiplayer's starting to go good.
I've got player connect/disconnect going
and map streaming on login."
- [Narrator] With the
release of multiplayer,
nearly a month had passed
of constant updates,
fine-tuning and debugging
since "Minecraft" was first introduced
to the TIGSource community.
And Persson realized
that his passion project
could be much more
than just a game he was making as a hobby.
If it was going to
continue to grow like this,
it was time to put a price
tag on it and go commercial.
Though today, it may
seem completely normal
that an indie developer sells their game
rather than releasing it for free,
this wasn't actually the
case in the late 2000s.
The expected practice rather,
was to release a game as freeware
and to make money through the use of ads.
Persson, however, came
up with a different plan.
Having seen how valuable
the direct feedback
from the forum has been,
he designed his pricing
to reward early adopters.
And despite the warning
that people wouldn't pay for such a game,
sales started coming
in almost immediately.
Persson even started seeing
such a high influx in his income
that his PayPal account was
frozen due to suspected fraud.
It was also enough that he was able
to change his status from
full-time to part-time at jAlbum,
allowing him to spend even more time
on developing "Minecraft."
Month after month, Persson
followed the same process,
listening to feedback from
those who were playing,
implementing more features
that were commonly requested
and fixing any bugs that were reported.
He also during this
time met another person
on the TIGSource forum
that could help him with
the game's sound design.
Daniel Rosenfeld is a
musician and sound engineer,
and he began to collaborate with Persson
to provide sound effects for "Minecraft"
as well as produce the iconic soundtrack
that is still used to this day.
By 2010, sales of "Minecraft"
had grown to the point
where Persson was able
to quit his part-time job
with jAlbum altogether.
And it was clear that as
"Minecraft" continued to expand,
Persson would need an
actual business structure
to handle the explosive growth.
But since he was uninterested
in actually running a business,
he decided to call in some help.
First was a friend and colleague
from Persson's old days
at Midas Player, Jakob Porser.
Second was yet another colleague,
but this time from jAlbum,
the former CEO Carl Manneh.
Together, the three would
establish the company
that would officially
back "Minecraft," Mojang.
Persson was no longer working from home,
but had built a small team.
The game was still not
officially finished,
but it already became immensely
popular amongst players.
And by August of 2010,
Minecraft had grown enough
to catch the attention
of other much larger game
developing companies,
such as Valve.
Persson was invited for
meeting to the headquarters
of the gaming giant in
Bellevue, Washington,
and he accepted the meeting
halfway across the world.
And while there, Persson
thought he could also meet
some "Minecraft" fans.
- [Markus] "I have all day on
August 31st free in Bellevue
if you guys could organize
something on the forums,
and I figured we could
call it MinecraftCon 2010,
even if it's just three
people sitting around
in uncomfortable silence for 20 minutes."
- [Narrator] During
the meeting with Valve,
the company offered Persson a position.
However, he decided to turn the offer down
as his focus was solely on Minecraft.
After these negotiations, however,
Persson joined a small gathering of people
that had come around
because of his blog post.
A little more than 50 people turned up
to hang out in a park,
a meetup that would go down as
the very first MinecraftCon,
and this spontaneous event
would give the Mojang team an idea.
By the end of 2010,
"Minecraft" had reached
over 700,000 sales,
and yet by this point,
"Minecraft" was still
technically not a finished game.
It was still in its beta phase,
but Mojang's development team
was close to finishing the actual release.
With so much hype already
built around the game,
Mojang knew they needed some fanfare
to go along with the game's launch.
And in November, 2011,
they decided to host an official MineCon.
This time, instead of an
impromptu gathering of 50 people,
it would be a sold out organized
event with 4,500 attendees.
And in quintessential early 2010s fashion,
this Minecraft convention
had a party DJ'd by Deadmau5.
(bouncy music)
All of this would be leading
up to the grand finale
of MineCon 2011,
the official release of the game.
As the Mojang team gathered on stage,
Persson would stand by
a large blocky lever,
and with one pull, "Minecraft"
was officially launched
as a finished project.
Even though the game was now finished,
the team would continue working
on it, releasing updates,
and adding new features even until today.
But for a Persson himself,
it was the end of a chapter.
After two years of continuous
work on "Minecraft,"
he was ready to move on to other projects
in order to get back to what
he loved doing most, coding.
And so just two weeks
after "Minecraft"'s official release,
Persson decided to step
down from his position
as lead developer of "Minecraft."
With Jens Bergensten now at its helm,
"Minecraft" continued to flourish,
but Persson didn't get the
rest he was hoping for.
Still perceived as the
maker of "Minecraft,"
players continued to send any issues
they encountered to him,
and he was flooded by complaints.
For a long time,
he would attempt to ignore
the negative feedback
that he could do nothing about
until it finally came to a head in 2014.
As the popularity of
"Minecraft" continued exploding,
an inevitable feature from
players began to emerge,
pay to win.
Mojang has always allowed
public servers to be created
so that players around the world
can play the same map together.
However, this opened a door
for some to take advantage
and create servers where players
have to spend money to gain an advantage.
These pay to win services
violated the end user license
agreement of "Minecraft,"
which is why in a controversial move,
Mojang began to crack
down on these servers
and gave them a deadline to
either adapt or to shut down.
Following this statement by Mojang,
there was immense negative feedback.
And though Persson was no
longer working on "Minecraft,"
he still received the
bulk of the criticism.
In frustration, he sent out
a tweet on June 17th, 2014,
that would change the
direction of Mojang forever.
- [Markus] "Anyone want
to buy my share of Mojang
so I can move on with my life?
Getting hate for trying
to do the right thing
is not my gig."
- [Narrator] The very next day,
Manneh began fielding calls from companies
that wanted to know if
Persson was serious,
including studio giants EA,
Activision and Microsoft.
And after giving it a thought,
Persson realized he actually was serious
about selling Mojang
so that he could finally
distance himself completely.
And after several rounds of
negotiations, a deal was struck.
- Mojang has confirmed it's
being sold to Microsoft
for $2.5 billion.
- [Narrator] The deal with Microsoft
meant that the Mojang
founders Persson, Manneh,
and Porser would step away completely,
whereas all of their employees
would be barred from layoffs.
The Microsoft deal was worth
a staggering $2.5 billion.
And as the major shareholder of Mojang,
Persson had become a
billionaire overnight.
(upbeat electronic music)
This is the part of the script
that should have been
the easiest to write.
After all, it's a classic happy ending.
Persson had achieved the unthinkable.
He turned his passion
project started at home
into an empire, becoming
wealthier than he ever imagined.
In the following years,
Persson would continue developing games
and he would do what billionaires do,
moving to Los Angeles
and buying the most expensive mansion
ever built in Beverly Hills,
hosting extravagant parties.
Meanwhile, "Minecraft"
continues to thrive.
With over 300 million sales,
it is to this day the most
sold video game ever made.
But yet, this is the part
of the script for this video
that was by far the hardest to write.
In 2017, a series of racist
and homophobic tweets
led to Microsoft distancing
itself from Persson.
They scrubbed his name from the game
and did not invite him
to the 10th anniversary
celebration of "Minecraft."
Persson's tweets were bad, really bad,
and they have significantly impacted
his legacy in recent years.
For me, the hard part
about writing this section
is figuring out how to talk
about someone's harmful comments
without making things worse.
In situations like this,
it often feels like there are
two paths someone can take.
The easy path is the one
where they double down
on their harmful views,
find a crowd that supports them.
But then there is the hard path,
acknowledging the mistakes,
learning from them,
and making an effort to change.
And the easier we make it for people
to take this second path,
the more might take it.
Markus Persson's story
is undeniably inspiring.
There are few stories that
highlight as well as this
how powerful a good idea is
and how much creativity can flourish
within constraints as his.
And more than anything,
he has created a world
that I've always experienced
as incredibly inclusive.
When is "Minecraft" the most fun?
Is it when you open a new world,
starting to build
something new from scratch?
Or is it when you've built an empire
and when you have an abundance
of everything there is?
Markus Persson is now in
that second stage of life.
(mouse clicking)
When I first started this channel,
I never could have imagined
it would lead to making videos like this.
I got to hire an actor, build out a set,
and even rent a sound stage
in order to make this story come to life.
And over the course of the last years,
I have produced my most
ambitious productions yet.
My video series called Under Exposure,
each episode a unique gripping story
that I believe deserves to be highlighted.
The series name Under
Exposure is intentional.
An underexposed image is a photograph
that captures too few
details in the shadows.
But in my series,
we will bring these
shadowy aspects to life
to find out what really happened
on the top floor of
the Bin Laden compound,
why flight MH17 crashed
over Eastern Ukraine.
Or look at the remarkable story
of how two families escaped a dictatorship
using only a self-made hot air balloon.
This entire series is available
exclusively on Nebula,
which is a creator-owned streaming service
where the likes of Johnny
Harris, Wendover Productions,
or Real Life Lore post
their videos early ad-free
and create higher budget originals,
such as my original series.
So go to nebula.tv/neo
and make sure that you
use exactly this link
in order to get 40% off the annual plan.
All my exclusive videos are up there,
so thanks for the support
and thank you so much
for watching this video.